Finding aid for the Getty Research Institute Poetry Initiatives Records, 1997-2005, undated IA60007
Institutional Records and Archives
Getty Research Institute poetry initiatives records
1997-2005, undated
Institutional Records and Archives
Clough, Jeanette Marie
Getty Research Institute
Poetry Society of America
Los Angeles County Metropolitan Transportation Authority
Santa Monica (Calif.). Arts Commission
Occidental College
Friends of the Los Angeles River
Beyond Baroque Literary Arts Center
IA60007
1 Linear Feet (2 boxes)
0.0004 GB (15 files)
The records comprise paper and electronic project files documenting various poetry initiatives sponsored by the Getty Research Institute (GRI) dating from 1997 to 2005 such as Poetry in Motion® L.A as well as GRI-commissioned poems related to the Scholars Program. Records include correspondence, ephemera of poetry readings, press materials, poet biographies, poems, and planning documents.
Scope and Contents
The records comprise printed and electronic records that date from 1997 to 2005, undated and document various poetry initiatives sponsored by the Getty Research Institute, such as Poetry in Motion and GRI-commissioned poems related to the Scholars Program.
Materials include event and initiative planning materials, correspondence, copies of commissioned poems, poet biographies, and ephemera. Materials were maintained by Jeanette Clough, Senior Reference Librarian at the Getty Research Institute.
Access Restrictions
The records described in accessions 2012.IA.054 and 2017.IA.35 are available for on-site use by qualified researchers. The following types of records are permanently closed: records containing personal information, records that compromise security or operations, legal communications, legal work product, and records related to donors. The J. Paul Getty Trust reserves the right to restrict access to any records held by the Institutional Archives.
Acquisition Information
Accessions 2012.IA.054 and 2017.IA.35 were transferred by staff members at the Getty Research Institute.
Arrangement
The records are arranged in chronological order.
Administrative History and Project Background
The Getty Research Institute (GRI) is an operating program of the J. Paul Getty Trust, a not-for-profit educational, cultural and philanthropic organization dedicated to the visual arts. Originally established in 1983 as the Getty Center for the History of Art and the Humanities (GCHAH), the objective of the GCHAH was to foster advanced research in art, its history, diversity, and meaning in culture by engaging scholars from various disciplines in the humanities. In 1996, in order to avoid confusion with the soon-to-open Getty Center, the GCHAH was renamed the Getty Research Institute for the History of Art and the Humanities and in 2000, the program's name was shortened to the Getty Research Institute (GRI).
The GRI's mission is to further knowledge and advance understanding of the visual arts and their various histories through advanced research and scholarship, and through its activities and resources, provide a unique environment for research, critical inquiry, and scholarly exchange. The GRI's Research Library, consisting of over one million books, periodicals, study photographs, auction catalogs and special collections of rare and unique materials, as well as its online resources and databases, serve an international community of scholars and the interested public. The GRI also provides intellectual leadership through its research projects, exhibitions, and publication programs and provides service to a wide range of scholars worldwide through residencies, fellowships, hosted lectures and symposia, and its innovative digital reference tools. Through all of its programs and activities, the GRI endeavors to provide resources, expertise, and a collaborative environment for art-historical research and publication.
Through multidisciplinary programming from the department of Contemporary Programs and Research (CPR) and its successor, the Department of Architecture and Contemporary Art (DACA), the GRI advanced art history scholarship of contemporary art. As part of this effort CPR, along with the GRI Office of the Associate Director of Programs, sponsored various poetry initiatives. One such initiative was Poetry in Motion ® L.A. Originally founded in New York in 1992, it was brought to Los Angeles through a partnership founded in 1998 with the Poetry Society of America, the Getty Research Institute, the City of Santa Monica, and the Los Angeles County Metropolitan Transportation Authority, Metro Art. Poets staged live readings of poetry in the Metro Rail system at rush hour in celebration of National Poetry Month. Additionally, the work of poets were inscribed on placards placed aboard nearly 2,400 Metro buses servicing over one million bus riders per day.
In another partnership with outside institutions including Occidental College, Friends of the Los Angeles River, and Beyond Baroque, the GRI commissioned poems from seven poets about the Los Angeles River for Occidental College and Friends of the Los Angeles River 's "Re-Envisioning the Los Angeles River," a year-long series of events promoting community education and economic revitalization.
Lastly, in conjunction with the GRI Scholar Program, the GRI commissioned poems from American poets from 1999 to 2002. The commissioned poems addressed the theme of each Scholar Program year and were presented in public and private readings at the Getty.
Technical Requirements
A computer with network access is needed to view the electronic files in accession 2012.IA.054 at file:///A:\ 2012_ia_54.
American poetry; Poetry, Modern -- 20th century; Los Angeles River (Calif.); Clough, Jeanette Marie; Antin, David; Brock-Broido, Lucie; Emanuel, Lynn, 1949-; Goldbarth, Albert; Hirsch, Edward; Kelly, Brigit Pegeen, 1951-; Kinnell, Galway, 1927-2014; Lux, Thomas, 1946-2017; McHugh, Heather, 1948-; Santos, Sherod, 1948-; Troupe, Quincy; Clifton, Lucille, 1936-2010; Hirshfield, Jane, 1953-; Kizer, Carolyn; Merwin, W. S. (William Stanley), 1927-2019; Wakoski, Diane; Bell, Marvin, 1937-; Waldman, Anne, 1945-; St. John, David, 1949-; Webb, Charles Harper; Angel, Ralph, 1951-; Hall, Donald, 1928-2018
- Paper records, 1997-2002; Series I.; 1 Linear Feet (2 boxes)
  Scope and Contents
  The records date from 1997 to 2002 and comprise paper planning documents for the various poetry initiatives and readings held at the Getty. Materials include correspondence, event planning materials, poet biographies, and copies of poems.
  Arrangement
  The records are arranged in chronological order.
  - Poetry project binder: Lucie Brock-Broido, Lynn Emanuel, Albert Goldbarth, Edward Hirsch, Brigit Pegeen Kelly, Galway Kinnell, Thomas Lux, Heather McHugh, Jane Miller, Carol Muske, Holly Peacock, Robert Pinksky, Sherod Santos, Quincy Troupe, Charles Wright, 1997-1998 (Box 2012.IA.054-01)
  - Press Kit: Poetry in Motion, 1997-1998 (Box 2012.IA.054-01)
  - Commissioned poems: Lucille Clifton, Jane Hirshfield, Carolyn Kizer, W.S. Merwin, Diane Wakoski, 1998 (Box 2012.IA.054-01)
  - Commissioned poems, 1999-2001 (Box 2012.IA.054-01)
  - PSA/Other, 1999-2003 (Box 2012.IA.054-01)
  - Commissioned rdg, 2001-2002 (Box 2012.IA.054-01)
  - [Visions of Bound-ries: An Evening with Three American Poets]: opening remarks, floppy disk, poems, April 26, 2002 (Box 2012.IA.054-01)
- Electronic Records, 1998-2005; Series II.; 0.0004 GB (15 files)
  The records date from 1998 to 2005 and comprise electronic files documenting the various poetry initiatives and readings held at the Getty. Materials include correspondence, event planning materials, poet biographies, and copies of poems.
  Technical Requirements
  A computer with network access is needed to view the electronic files in accession 2012.IA.054 at http://hdl.handle.net/10020/2012ia054.
  - Other poems, 1998-2005
  - Poetry Society of America, 2002-2003
  - GRI commissioned poems, 2002-2004